<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[DEBUGGIFY]]></title>
  <link href="http://debuggify.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://debuggify.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-28T03:29:54+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://debuggify.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Debuggify]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Debuggify?]]></title>
    <link href="http://debuggify.github.com/blog/2012/08/07/why-debuggify/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-07T12:10:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://debuggify.github.com/blog/2012/08/07/why-debuggify</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To be frank, Internet is a second home to me. I was born 6 years back when I bought my first computer and a internet connection. For most of people out there who feel same, are continuously trying to make <em>Internet a better place</em>. I am also a computer science engineering grad so my affinity towards computers is justified. In order to feed my engineering inquisitiveness and my quest to make the Internet a better place, I have explored the black, white and gray sections of the internet.</p>

<p>I am full stack web developer by profession and have authored / coauthored many 3rd party social plugins for <a href="http://www.shareaholic.com/publishers">Shareaholic Inc</a> which runs on thousands of different blogs and websites driving 1+ billion pageviews per month. These plugins can be installed on different CMS/blogging platform like Wordpress, Drupal, Tumblr, Blogger etc. While working on these plugins I closely interact with the different elements of the modern internet ecosystem.</p>

<p>What&#8217;s my use case of 3rd party plugin ?</p>

<blockquote><p>A 3rd party plugin has to be <strong>robust</strong> enough to work in <strong>3rd party environments</strong> while interacting with <strong>3rd party apis</strong> and support every <strong>major browser vendor</strong> out there</p></blockquote>

<p>Explaining the above quote</p>

<ul>
<li>As plugins runs on 3rd party websites, it has to be robust so it <code>doesn't break</code> itself and neither the website</li>
<li>It has to be fast enough to deliver <code>good page load time</code></li>
<li>It should <code>not conflict</code> with other existing plugins</li>
<li>It should <code>support majour browser vendors</code> including internet explorer</li>
<li>It should also <code>support legacy browser versions</code> like ie6 ie7 etc</li>
<li>As plugins interact with over 200+ 3rd party apis, it hard to keep track when something break</li>
<li>It should be easy to setup with multiple cms/blogging environments for better distribution</li>
</ul>


<p>I have faced many <code>technical challenges</code> while developing these plugins, some of them</p>

<ul>
<li>In 3rd party environment, developers have limited or no control over things, so its hard to debug and reproduce bugs / issues</li>
<li>If some plugin feature is not working its hard to know whether

<ul>
<li>its not working for a particular website,</li>
<li>or not working for a set of URLs</li>
<li>or for a particular CMS/Blogging environment</li>
<li>or for a particular screen resolution</li>
<li>or for a particular browser vendor</li>
<li>or even for a particular version of a browser vendor</li>
<li>or for all cases</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Its hard to judge the impact of every release, whether it fixed the problem or introduced some new side effects</li>
<li>The 3rd party API&#8217;s are continuously changing, upgrading &amp; depreciating.  Companies like Facebook, Google, Twitter are continuously bashing developers with bleeding edges of their API&#8217;s</li>
<li>With HTML5, ES Harmony and CSS3,  browsers are evolving faster than ever, so they are also releasing bleeding edge features and API&#8217;s</li>
</ul>


<p><code>Web developers</code> are the keepers of the modern internet. They are encountering similar problems on the daily basic. A majority their development time is spend in debugging and fixing bugs. The debugging is becoming hard due to the evolving nature of web and Zero Bugs is a Myth. So I finally decided to go on a quest to make <strong>Internet a better place for developers</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
